<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Appium on Andrew&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://andrewu.page/tags/appium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Appium on Andrew&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>Andrew&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://andrewu.page/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://andrewu.page/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 12:44:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andrewu.page/tags/appium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Install Robot Framework and Appium on Mac OS?</title>
      <link>https://andrewu.page/2022/04/install-robot-framework-and-appium-on-mac-os/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 12:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://andrewu.page/2022/04/install-robot-framework-and-appium-on-mac-os/</guid>
      <description>You have to install Xcode first.
Open a terminal and verify Python and pip installation.
We can use this to check our python on Mac OS
which python # to check python2 which python3 # to check python3 Then use the pip3 list to check our installed list.
And then, we use pip3 to install the robot framework.
pip3 install robotframework Run pip3 list to check robotframwork is in our list.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You have to install Xcode first.</p>
<p>Open a terminal and verify Python and pip installation.</p>
<p>We can use this to check our python on Mac OS</p>
<pre><code>which python # to check python2
which python3 # to check python3
</code></pre>
<p>Then use the pip3 list to check our installed list.</p>
<p>And then, we use pip3 to install the robot framework.</p>
<pre><code>pip3 install robotframework
</code></pre>
<p>Run pip3 list to check robotframwork is in our list.</p>
<p>After running the <code>robot —version</code> to check that the installation was successful.</p>
<p>Now that the robot framework has been installed; we can install robotframework-appiumlibrary, use pip3.</p>
<pre><code>pip3 install robotframework-appiumlibrary
</code></pre>
<p>Install Java JDK from the Oracle website to download the version that suits your Mac OS</p>
<p>Install Android Studio from the site to download the version that suits your Mac OS</p>
<p>And install homebrew and use the command from their home page as below command:</p>
<pre><code>/bin/bash -c &quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>After homebrew is installed, we can use homebrew to install node and appium, use commands:</p>
<pre><code>brew install node
brew install appium
</code></pre>
<p>Open Android SDK manager, go to Android SDK to install SDK tools, we will install as below list:</p>
<ul>
<li>Android SDK Build-Tools</li>
<li>Android SDK Command-line Tools</li>
<li>Android Emulator</li>
<li>Android SDK Platform-Tools</li>
<li>Google Play services</li>
<li>Android SDK Tools</li>
</ul>
<p>Checked what we will want to install, then press the <code>Apply</code> button to download these tools.</p>
<p>Now we can write our path file to .zsh_profile for JAVA_HOME and ANDROID_HOME, the file content would be like this:</p>
<pre><code># JAVA
export JAVA_HOME=/Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.8.0_321.jdk/Contents/Home
export PATH=$JAVA_HOME/bin:$PATH

# ANDROID
export ANDROID_HOME=/Users/username/Library/Android/sdk
export PATH=$ANDROID_HOME/platform-tools:$PATH
export PATH=$ANDROID_HOME/tools:$PATH
export PATH=$ANDROID_HOME/tools/bin:$PATH
export PATH=$ANDROID_HOME/emulator:$PATH
</code></pre>
<p>After we saved this file, we have to type <code>source .zsh_profile</code> to
execute commands from this file.</p>
<p>Then we can type the below commands to check our installations.</p>
<pre><code>java -version
node —version
npm -version
appium -v
adb —version
</code></pre>
<p>If the above commands show well, we can install the appium-doctor to check our environment is correct for appium, use npm to install it, the command is:</p>
<pre><code>npm install appium-doctor -g
</code></pre>
<p>After installation of appium-doctor, you can run this command to check your environment.</p>
<pre><code>appium-doctor
</code></pre>
<p>If any necessary dependencies are installed, means your environment is done now, Congratulations！</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robot Framework And Appium Install Environment On Windows</title>
      <link>https://andrewu.page/2022/04/robot-framework-and-appium-install-environment-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://andrewu.page/2022/04/robot-framework-and-appium-install-environment-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>For Robot Framework and Appium environment on Windows, we should install softwares list below:
Robot Framework node JDK Android Studio Appium Appium Desktop appium-doctor First of all we have to install Java JDK for me I will need the Windows 64 bit. Java Downloads JDK And we chose the x64 Installer for our environment.
The installation is very simple we just press next, next and finish, then we can go to setting our environment.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For Robot Framework and Appium environment on Windows, we should install softwares list below:</p>
<ul>
<li>Robot Framework</li>
<li>node</li>
<li>JDK</li>
<li>Android Studio</li>
<li>Appium</li>
<li>Appium Desktop</li>
<li>appium-doctor</li>
</ul>
<p>First of all we have to install Java JDK for me I will need the Windows 64 bit.
<a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/technologies/downloads/#jdk18-windows">Java Downloads JDK</a>
And we chose the x64 Installer for our environment.</p>
<p>The installation is very simple we just press next, next and finish, then we can go to setting our environment.</p>
<p>We have to create a new system variable as below:</p>
<pre><code>Variable name: JAVE_HOME
Variable value: C:\Program Files\Java\jdk-18 # base on you jdk path
</code></pre>
<p>After Java JDK installed, we need to install our Android Studio.
<a href="https://developer.android.com/studio?gclid=CjwKCAjwrqqSBhBbEiwAlQeqGhB3kESe_97wBHxGA5_3DnKIc9L51tsNIAQ6CNZOTmnaQgR3M2PpjxoCPnoQAvD_BwE&amp;gclsrc=aw.ds">Android Studio</a>
Then downloaded Android Studio, we used the default settings and finished our installation.</p>
<p>And open our Android Studio and go to SDK Manager to download our Android SDK, then go to setting our environment too.</p>
<p>Create a new user variable as below:</p>
<pre><code>Variable name: ANDROID_HOME
Variable value: C:\Users\username\AppData\Local\Android\Sdk # you can find in SDK Manager page
</code></pre>
<p>Then edit Path variable in user variables and add new variables as below:
%ANDROID_HOME%\tools
%ANDROID_HOME%\build-tools
%ANDROID_HOME%\emulator
%ANDROID_HOME%\tools\bin</p>
<p>Finished Android Studio installation, we can install our node now.
<a href="https://nodejs.org/en/download/">node download</a>
During the installation we have to make sure at Custom Setup section has &ldquo;Add to PATH&rdquo; below.</p>
<p>Now we installed node, we can go to download our Appium now.</p>
<p>Because we alraedy installed node, we can open our cmd and type below commands to check our node and npm versions:</p>
<pre><code>node -v
npm -v
</code></pre>
<p>Make sure they show you your installed version number, then we can use npm to install our Appium.</p>
<p>The Appium install command likes below:
npm install appium -g</p>
<p>Check your appium installation, use command as below:
appium &ndash;version</p>
<p>Finally we can use npm to install appium-doctor to check our environment, we use the command below to install:
npm intaal -g appium-doctor</p>
<p>After installed appium-doctor, use <code>appium-doctor --version</code> to check your installation was successeful.</p>
<p>Then we can open a new cmd to check our appium environment, use the command below:
appium-doctor</p>
<p>Sometimes we like to use some GUI application, so we also can download Appium Desktop application.</p>
<p>We can go to <a href="https://appium.io/">Appium</a> site to download the GUI option.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s easy to install, just press next, next and finish.</p>
<p>After that you can launch your Appium Desktop Application.</p>
<p>Check you were installed successful.</p>
<p>Finally we have to download &ldquo;Robot Framework&rdquo;, you have to download python on you Windows first, after that use <code>pip install robotframework</code> to installing Robot Framework.</p>
<p>To check that the installation was successful, run:
robot &ndash;version</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
